Okay, moving on to the adrenal gland.
Recall that the adrenal gland is actually two organs in one.
There's an adrenal cortex,
which secretes hormones derived from cholesterol,
and then there is an adrenal medulla,
and the medulla, of course, secretes catecholamines,
such as epinephrine and norepinephrine.
We're going to begin our discussion with the adrenal cortex,
and then we're going to move on to the medulla.
Now, before we can discuss the cortex,
you need a little bit of background,
and so let's recall from histology
that the adrenal cortex actually has three layers,
a glomerulosa, a fasciculata, and a reticularis.
Now, that's pretty easy to remember.
One of the mnemonics that people like to use is GFR.
Remember that the adrenals sit on top of the kidney,
and, of course, in the kidney,
one of the key things that we always talk about is a GFR,
and so it shouldn't be hard to remember
that in the adrenal gland,
you're also going to think about GFR.
Again, glomerulosa, fasciculata, reticularis.
Now, you also need to remember
that all of the hormones that are produced by the cortex
are going to be derived from cholesterol.
In fact, if you recall from anatomy,
when you look at the adrenal,
it has a very distinct yellow color,
and that's because it's loaded with cholesterol,
which is eventually going to be used
to make all of these hormones.
Now, cholesterol in the glomerulosa
will eventually generate mineralocorticoids,
such as aldosterone,
and, of course, aldosterone is important
for salt maintenance.
Cholesterol will also eventually generate cortisol,
and cholesterol will also eventually generate
the sex steroids.
And one of the mnemonics that some students like to use
to remember this is, quote, unquote,
it gets sweeter as you get deeper,
i.e., this is salt, this is sugar,
because cortisol is important for maintaining sugar as well,
and this represents sex steroids.
And so I tell you that the adrenal gland
is composed of three layers,
glomerulosa, fasciculata, reticularis,
and, of course, the glomerulosa generates mineralocorticoids,
such as aldosterone.
The fasciculata generates glucocorticoids,
such as cortisol,
and the reticularis generates sex steroids.
The first disorder is Cushing syndrome,
and in Cushing syndrome, we have an excess of cortisol.
The clinical features of Cushing syndrome
will all be based on the physiology of cortisol.
One of the important things that cortisol does
is to raise the blood sugar,
and one way by which it does this
is to break down muscle for gluconeogenesis.
So patients with Cushing syndrome
are gonna have muscle weakness with thin extremities,
and, again, that's because you're breaking down muscle
to provide the amino acids necessary for gluconeogenesis.
In addition, the patients will have moon facies,
buffalo hump, and truncal obesity.
Now, the idea here is that if you have gluconeogenesis,
you're gonna have a high glucose in the blood.
The high glucose is gonna result in excess insulin
being produced by the pancreas.
The excess insulin will then result in the storage of fat,
and so fat will be stored in the face,
on the back, and on the trunk.
An additional consequence
is that the patients will develop abdominal striae.
The reason for this is that cortisol
impairs the synthesis of collagen,
and so when you have weak collagen,
the blood vessels can rupture easily,
and so you'll get these striae on the abdomen,
which basically represent ruptured blood vessels.
The patients can also develop hypertension.
The idea here is that cortisol upregulates
alpha-1 receptors on the arterioles,
which then increases the effect of norepinephrine.
Remember that cortisol is necessary for life,
and the reason it's necessary for life
is because it helps to maintain vascular tone,
and so the way by which it maintains vascular tone
is upregulation of alpha-1 receptors on arterioles,
and so when you have excess cortisol,
you'll have excess alpha-1 receptors,
which will then increase the effect of norepinephrine,
giving the patients hypertension.
That's particularly high yield.
The patients can also develop osteoporosis,
and finally, the patients can also get immune suppression,
and we're well aware of the fact
that cortisol is used as an immunosuppressant,
but it's important to go back and remind ourselves why,
and so there's three major mechanisms
by which cortisol results in immune suppression.
Number one is that it inhibits phospholipase A2,
and recall that if you inhibit phospholipase A2,
you won't be able to generate
your arachidonic acid metabolites,
and of course, those are essential for inflammation.
Number two is that it inhibits IL-2,
and IL-2 is an important T-cell growth factor,
and number three is that it inhibits
release of histamine from mast cells,
and of course, histamine is essential for vasodilation
and for increased vascular permeability,
and so all three of these are mechanisms
by which you get immune suppression
in patients with Cushing syndrome.
The diagnosis of Cushing syndrome
is made by detecting an increased
24-hour urine cortisol level,
and when you think about the causes of Cushing syndrome,
there's actually four major causes.
The first would be exogenous corticosteroids,
and so the idea here
is that we prescribed corticosteroids to the patient,
and as a result of that excess corticosteroids,
the patient will develop Cushing syndrome.
This is actually the most common cause
of Cushing syndrome,
and one of the important consequences
with exogenous corticosteroids
is that both adrenal glands, in this case,
will actually become atrophic.
Now, let's just go back and remind ourselves.
When you have excess cortisol within the blood,
that cortisol will go to the anterior pituitary
and shut down the production of ACTH.
When you shut down the production of ACTH,
that's then gonna result
in both adrenal glands becoming small,
and so you'll have bilateral adrenal atrophy
with exogenous corticosteroids.
A second possible cause of Cushing syndrome
could be some adrenal problem.
For example, you can have an adenoma,
you can have hyperplasia,
or you can have a carcinoma within the adrenal,
and that could produce cortisol,
and so in this particular case,
what's going to happen,
the high cortisol obviously
would give you Cushing syndrome,
but what's gonna happen is
one adrenal will be big,
and this is, for example,
the adrenal gland that has the adenoma.
That adrenal is going to be secreting cortisol.
Cortisol will then go into the blood.
It'll then go and hit the anterior pituitary.
That'll shut down ACTH,
and when it shuts down ACTH,
the opposite adrenal will actually become atrophic,
and so one adrenal gland will be big,
i.e. the one that has, for example,
the adenoma,
and the other will be atrophic.
A third way by which we can develop Cushing syndrome
would be to have an ACTH-secreting pituitary adenoma.
Now, in this particular case,
what's going to happen is
that the adenoma and the pituitary
will secrete ACTH.
The ACTH will hit both adrenals
when it goes into the blood
and make both adrenals big.
Now, when both adrenals are hit by ACTH,
both adrenals will produce excess cortisol,
and that excess cortisol
will obviously result in Cushing syndrome.
The fourth possibility
is to have peroneoplastic ACTH secretion.
Now, in this particular case,
you have a tumor.
The most classic example
would be a small cell carcinoma of the lung.
The tumor secretes ACTH.
That ACTH goes into the blood.
It hits both adrenals.
When it hits both adrenals,
both adrenals will then become large,
and both adrenals will produce cortisol,
which will result in Cushing syndrome.
Now, notice that
when you look at these four possibilities,
this possibility is unique
in the sense that it's the only one
that gives you atrophy of both adrenals.
And this is unique
in the sense that you'd see one adrenal large
with a mass and the other adrenal atrophic.
However, when you look at these two,
you can't distinguish
based on the size of the adrenals.
And so you can actually do an additional test
to try to distinguish
an ACTH secreting pituitary adenoma
from ACTH secretion that arises
from, for example,
a small cell carcinoma of the lung.
And the way by which you do this
would be to do a high-dose
dexamethasone suppression test.
The idea here is that
when you give high-dose dexamethasone,
which is a cortisol analog,
it has the ability
to suppress ACTH production
by a pituitary adenoma.
However, it will not be able
to suppress ectopic ACTH production
by a small cell carcinoma of the lung.
The way I think about this
is sort of the high-dose dexamethasone
gets into the blood,
it goes up to the pituitary adenoma,
and it slaps the pituitary adenoma
and says, wake up,
you're actually still
a benign pituitary cell.
And so then the pituitary adenoma
responds by shutting down
its ACTH production.
However, when high-dose dexamethasone
goes up to the small cell carcinoma
of the lung and tries
to slap it back into shape,
the small cell carcinoma of the lung
just slaps it back
because it is a cancer.
It is not going to listen to
or respond to anyone.
And so therefore,
high-dose dexamethasone
will not shut down ACTH production
by the small cell carcinoma
of the lung.
The final point is that
when you do this
high-dose dexamethasone suppression test,
you'll actually follow the effect
by measuring cortisol levels.
So the dexamethasone
will then decrease
the ACTH production
by the adenoma, for example,
which will then decrease
the amount of cortisol
being produced,
and so you'll be able
to detect decreased cortisol levels.
Hyper-aldosteronism
is when you have excess aldosterone,
and the effects of excess aldosterone
will all be based
on the normal physiology
of aldosterone.
So let's go back
and just remind ourselves
before we go to the text
that aldosterone works
on the late distal tubule
and the collecting duct.
And in this region,
there are two main cell types.
There is the principal cell
and there is
the alpha-intercalated cell.
Now the principal cell
in response to aldosterone
will actually grab sodium
and will dump potassium.
And the alpha-intercalated cell
in response to aldosterone
will actually dump hydrogen ion.
And so now you can imagine
that if a patient
has hyperaldosteronism,
they're going to get
hypernatremia
because they're grabbing sodium,
they're going to get
hypokalemia
because they're dumping potassium,
and they're going to get
a metabolic alkalosis
because they're dumping hydrogen ion.
And so this is the key findings,
as I've stated here in the text.
I say that the presentation
is hypernatremia,
you're grabbing sodium,
hypokalemia,
you're dumping potassium,
and a metabolic acidosis
because you're dumping hydrogen ion.
Now of course,
the patients will also have hypertension,
and that's because
when you grab sodium,
water is going to follow,
which is going to raise
the blood volume.
In primary hyperaldosteronism,
the high aldosterone
is due to a primary problem
within the adrenal gland,
and this would most commonly
be due to a benign tumor
of the adrenal gland
called an adrenal adenoma.
It is also possible
to have primary hyperaldosteronism
due to hyperplasia
or carcinoma
of the adrenal gland.
However,
these are much less common causes.
Now in this particular case,
you're going to have a high aldosterone
because you've got primary
hyperaldosteronism,
and you're going to have
a low renin.
Now recall that
when you have high aldosterone,
you're going to grab sodium,
and water is going to follow,
and that's going to raise
the blood volume.
That high blood volume
is then going to go
to the kidney,
so the kidney is going
to see high blood flow,
and so therefore,
it will decrease
the production of renin,
and so you'll have
a low renin,
and that's particularly high yield
when thinking about
primary hyperaldosteronism.
In secondary hyperaldosteronism,
you get a high aldosterone,
however,
it's secondary to the fact
that you have activated
the renin-angiotensin system.
Now recall from
our vascular lectures
that if this is the aorta,
and this is the renal artery,
and this is the kidney,
there's a couple ways
by which this could occur.
Classically,
in a young woman,
you can get something
called fibromuscular dysplasia,
which results in thickening
of the wall of the blood vessel,
which would then decrease
the blood flow to the kidney,
and therefore activate
the juxtaglomerular apparatus,
or you could get atherosclerosis,
particularly in elderly males,
which would then decrease
the blood flow to the kidney,
also activating
the juxtaglomerular apparatus.
Now recall from physiology
that when you activate
the JGA,
or the juxtaglomerular apparatus,
you're going to then
secrete renin,
so you're going to have
a high renin.
Of course,
the renin converts
angiotensinogen
to angiotensin 1.
Angiotensin 1
then gets converted
by angiotensin-converting enzyme
to angiotensin 2,
and then angiotensin 2
goes to the adrenal gland
and causes release
of aldosterone.
And so you're going
to have high aldosterone
because of the fact
that you activated
the renin-angiotensin system.
Congenital adrenal hyperplasia
is when you have hyperplasia
of both adrenal glands
due to a congenital defect
in the enzymes necessary
for steroidogenesis.
The most common deficiency
is a 21-hydroxylase deficiency.
However,
before you can understand this,
we need to go back
to the whiteboard.
Remember that cholesterol
is the starting point
for steroidogenesis
in the adrenal cortex.
It gets converted
to pregnenolone,
and pregnenolone
can enter into
one of three pathways.
It can produce
mineralocorticoids,
it can produce
cortisol,
or it can eventually
produce sex steroids.
Now,
in order to produce
mineralocorticoids,
you need 21-hydroxylase,
and in order to produce
cortisol,
you need 21-hydroxylase.
Imagine,
if there's a deficiency
of 21-hydroxylase
here and here,
then pregnenolone
will be shunted
to the preferential production
of sex steroids,
and so the sex steroids
will increase.
Now,
the consequence of this
is that the patient
can get clitoral enlargement
if they're a female,
or they can get
precocious puberty
if they're a male.
In addition,
there's going to be
a lack of cortisol
because you can't
produce cortisol.
This will result
in decreased cortisol
in the blood,
and the decreased cortisol
in the blood
can result in,
number one,
life-threatening hypotension,
because remember
that cortisol
is necessary for life,
and in particular,
it helps to maintain
vascular tone,
and so you can get
life-threatening hypotension,
and number two,
because you have
decreased cortisol,
you're going to have
decreased inhibitory feedback
on the anterior pituitary,
so there'll be
excess production
of ACTH.
The excess ACTH
will get into the blood,
it'll hit both adrenals
and make both adrenals
big,
and in fact,
that's why we call it
congenital adrenal hyperplasia.
Now, the third consequence
of having this defect
of 21-hydroxylase
will be that you won't
have mineralocorticoids.
When there's a loss
of aldosterone,
for example,
you'll get salt wasting.
Now, remember that
aldosterone normally
grabs salt
and dumps potassium,
so if you're lacking
aldosterone,
you're actually going
to lose salt,
i.e. salt wasting,
and you're going
to hold potassium,
and so the patients
will actually get
salt wasting
with hyponatremia
and hyperkalemia
because they're
holding potassium.
And at the same time,
normally because sodium
would come in
and water would follow,
in this case,
you're not going
to be bringing back sodium,
and so you're not
going to be bringing
back water,
and so the patients
can also become
hypovolemic.
Now, with this background
in mind,
let's go back
to the text.
Reduction of sex steroids
and the fact that
there'll be a deficiency
of cortisol
will lead to increased
ACTH from the anterior
pituitary.
Again, you're lacking
feedback on the anterior
pituitary,
which is then going
to result in bilateral
adrenal hyperplasia.
The clinical features
will be salt wasting.
Again, lack of aldosterone,
so you can't grab salt,
so you'll waste it
and you'll get hyponatremia
and you'll have hyperkalemia.
Again, normally aldosterone
would dump potassium,
but you're going
to hold potassium,
and there'll be hypovolemia
because you're not
bringing in salt.
There'll also be
life-threatening hypotension
because of the low cortisol,
and finally,
the patients can have
clitoral enlargement
if they're a female
or precocious puberty
in a male,
and that's because
of the increased
sex steroids.
Now, I'd like to actually
take this one step further,
although your text doesn't,
just to add a couple things
because it's easy
to do so here
and they're potentially
high-yield.
Let's just remind ourselves
that cholesterol
is a starting point
of steroidogenesis.
It can result
in the production
of pregnenolone,
and pregnenolone
can eventually enter
into one of three pathways.
It can lead
to the production
of mineralocorticoids
or cortisol
or sex steroids.
In order to produce cortisol,
you need both
21-hydroxylase
and 11-hydroxylase.
In order to produce
weak mineralocorticoids,
you need 21-hydroxylase,
and in order to produce
the next level
of mineralocorticoids,
you need 11-hydroxylase.
This is important
because remember,
when you lose 21-hydroxylase,
you don't produce
mineralocorticoids
and you don't produce
any cortisol,
and so the patients
have salt wasting
with all the symptoms
that I've already described.
However,
imagine if you had
an 11-hydroxylase deficiency.
You'd also not be able
to produce cortisol,
and you'd also get
some shunting
towards sex steroids.
However,
you would produce
a little bit
of a weak mineralocorticoid,
and so you wouldn't
have the salt wasting.
And so on board examination,
if they give you
the classic history
of someone with
a 21-hydroxylase deficiency,
however,
the patient doesn't
have salt wasting
and doesn't have
hyperkalemia
hypovolemia,
then you need to remember
that it's not
a 21-hydroxylase,
but instead,
it's an 11-hydroxylase problem,
and that's particularly
high yield,
so I'm taking a minute
to just explain that to you.
Cortisol and sex steroids,
you need 17-hydroxylase.
Now imagine,
if you're lacking
17-hydroxylase,
then you won't be able
to produce anything
on this side,
and the only thing
that you're going to produce
is excess mineralocorticoids,
and so if there's
a 17-hydroxylase deficiency,
the problem will be
excess mineralocorticoids
with no cortisol
and no sex steroids.
Now notice one thing,
and that is that
in all of these deficiencies,
17, 21, and 11,
you're always not
producing cortisol,
and so because you're
always not producing cortisol,
you're always going
to have excess ACTH
because of a lack
of feedback,
and so each of these cases
would result in
congenital adrenal hyperplasia.
Adrenal insufficiency
is when you have
a lack of adrenal hormones,
and adrenal insufficiency
can actually occur acutely
or can occur chronically.
When it's acute,
the classic high yield example
is Waterhouse-Friedrichsen syndrome.
This classically arises
in a young child
with a Neisseria meningitis infection
who develops DIC
and then gets bilateral necrosis
of both adrenal glands,
and of course,
that then results
in an acute lack of cortisol.
The acute lack of cortisol
would then exacerbate
the patient's hypotension.
Now, of course,
they've already got
Neisseria meningitis and DIC,
however, on top of that,
they then get this massive hypotension
due to a lack of cortisol,
and so this is particularly high yield.
Now here's a classic example.
Notice that this is
the adrenal gland here,
and you can see
that this adrenal gland
has been converted
to a sack of blood,
and that's the classic image
that they like to show.
It's a very common image
that shows up on board exams,
so the sack of blood adrenal,
and this again represents
Waterhouse-Friedrichsen syndrome
classically.
Chronic insufficiency
is when you get
slow progressive destruction
of the adrenal glands,
and there are three major causes
that are high yield
for the board exam.
The first is autoimmune destruction.
This is the most common cause
in the West.
The second is when
there's destruction of the adrenal glands
by TB,
and this is the most common cause
in the developing world,
and the third
is when there is metastatic carcinoma
that metastasizes to both adrenals,
and this is a very common cause
on board exams,
and the particular example here
that you want to bear in mind
is that lung cancer
loves to go to the adrenal,
very high yield.
Lung cancer
loves to go to the adrenal.
Now the clinical features
of chronic insufficiency
are going to be based
on a lack of the hormones
normally produced by the adrenal.
So you're going to get hypotension.
Why?
Because you don't have cortisol,
and cortisol is necessary
to maintain vascular tone.
You're going to get hyponatremia,
hypovolemia,
and hyperkalemia.
Again, you don't have aldosterone.
Aldosterone normally grabs sodium,
so because you don't have it,
you're going to dump sodium.
Aldosterone normally dumps potassium.
Because you don't have it,
you're going to hold potassium,
and because you don't have sodium,
you're also going to lose volume.
Patients can also get hyperpigmentation,
the idea here is that
if you don't have cortisol,
you're not going to be able
to negatively shut down
the production of ACTH
by the anterior pituitary,
so there'll be excess production
of ACTH.
Now ACTH is actually derived
from a molecule called POMC,
and one of the derivatives
of POMC is melanocyte-simulating hormone,
which will then stimulate
the melanocytes,
resulting in hyperpigmentation,
and it classically arises
in the oral mucosa,
but it'll also be present
on the skin.
And then the patients
also have vomiting and diarrhea,
again, due to a lack of cortisol.
Moving on to the adrenal medulla,
recall that the adrenal medulla
is composed of chromophane cells,
very high yield for board exams.
These are derived
from the neural crest.
They are the main physiologic source
of catecholamines,
and so both epinephrine
and norepinephrine
are released by the adrenal medulla.
The key pathology
that we want to cover
is called a pheochromocytoma.
A pheochromocytoma
is when you have a tumor
of the chromophane cells.
Now, when you get a tumor
of the chromophane cells,
the classic finding
on gross exam
and very high yield to know
is that you get a brown tumor.
Now, that's because
the adrenal medulla is brown,
and so if you get
this big tumor here
of the adrenal medulla,
of course,
it's also going to have
the same color,
which is brown.
Now, notice here
that you see this little yellow line
running along the edge
of the tumor,
and do you know what that is?
That little yellow line
represents the adrenal cortex.
And, of course,
the adrenal cortex
has a yellow color
because it's loaded
with cholesterol,
which is the starting point
for the production of steroids.
The clinical features
of pheochromocytoma
will be episodic hypertension,
headaches, palpitations,
tachycardia, and sweating.
All of these are a consequence
of epinephrine and norepinephrine.
The diagnosis is made
by detecting
increased serum metanephrines
and increased 24-hour urine
metanephrines in VMA.
Now, let's go back
to biochemistry
and remind ourselves
that if you have epinephrine
and norepinephrine,
the epinephrine
will be broken down
into metanephrine,
and the norepinephrine
will be broken down
into normetanephrine.
These two,
both metanephrine
and norepinephrine,
will be broken down
into VMA.
And, of course,
the enzyme that does this
is monoamine oxidase.
Now, this is particularly
high-yield biochemistry
because, of course,
if you've got a tumor
that's producing
epinephrine and norepinephrine,
then one way by which
you can make the diagnosis
is to detect
increased metanephrines
or increased VMA.
And so that's what we're saying
here in the text.
Let's go back to the book.
Diagnosed by increased
serum metanephrines
and increased 24-hour urine
metanephrines and VMA.
So, again,
that's particularly high-yield.
Now, the treatment
is surgical excision.
However, it's very high-yield
to know for the purposes
of board exams
that before you remove
the tumor,
you're going to give
the patient's
phenoxybenzamine,
which is an irreversible
blocker of alpha receptors.
Now, the idea here
is that when the surgeon
goes in to remove the tumor,
if they grab the tumor,
when they squeeze it,
they could actually squeeze out
epinephrine and norepinephrine.
That can result in massive
hypertension in the patient
and can actually result in death.
And so, in order to avoid
the effect of this surge
of epinephrine and norepinephrine,
patients are given
phenoxybenzamine
before the tumor is removed.
Additional features
of pheochromocytoma
are remembered
by the rules of 10.
10% are bilateral,
10% are familial,
10% are malignant,
i.e. 90% are benign,
and 10% are located
outside of the adrenal medulla.
Now, it's very high yield
to note that one classic location
outside of the adrenal medulla
would be the bladder wall.
And so, on a board exam,
if you have a patient
that when they urinate
develops episodic hypertension,
et cetera,
think about a pheochromocytoma
involving the wall
of the bladder.
And again,
that's particularly
high yield as well.
Now, a few associations
with pheochromocytoma
to close off this discussion.
The first is that
patients with both MEN2A
and MEN2B
can develop pheochromocytoma.
Just as a review
from earlier in this section,
remember that MEN2A
is medullary carcinoma
of the thyroid,
pheochromocytoma,
and parathyroid adenoma.
And that MEN2B
is medullary carcinoma
of the thyroid,
pheochromocytoma,
and mucosal ganglioneuromas,
especially in the oral mucosa.
Now, also remember
from earlier in this section
that the key thing
about MEN2 overall
is that medullary carcinoma
of the thyroid
is the key thing
that would kill the patient.
And so one way
we can avoid developing
the cancer
would be to remove
the thyroid.
And remember that
there's a key gene
that you want to test for
before you remove the thyroid
to determine
if there's a genetic risk.
And what's that gene?
RET.
Again, the association
of RET mutation
leading to medullary carcinoma
of the thyroid
is very high yield
for board exams.
Von Hippel-Lindau disease
is an autosomal dominant condition
where you lose
the von Hippel-Lindau
tumor suppressor gene.
We talked about this disease
in the renal section.
Remember that the patients
have an increased risk
of hemangioblastoma
of the cerebellum
and an increased risk
of renal cell carcinoma
and now I'm telling you
that there's an increased risk
of pheochromocytoma
in those patients as well.
And finally,
in neurofibromatosis type 1,
patients get neurofibromas
but they can also develop
pheochromocytomas.
And so that's an important
association
for board exams as well.
And that concludes
both this section
as well as the endocrine chapter.